It's parachuting in somewhere, stealing
a van, and snatching somebody off the
street, and then you meet the helicopter
at the departure point, and then just
fly the guy to wherever it is you're
going to fly him. It's very dangerous.
>> Were you at the agency when they stood
up the GRS program?
>> I was dating a woman who's soon to be
ex-husband was in GRS, and she said, "My
husband's a GRS officer." I said,
"What's GRS?" She looked at me kind of
funny and she told me and I said, "Oh
they've made it official."
>> What has been your experience with
Ground Branch and Special Activities and
whatever they're calling it now?
>> Honestly, my experience with all of
those special activities groups was
seeing them in the in the office and
saying, "Hope you had a good weekend."
Those guys, first of all, almost none of
them are career CIA officers. They had
long successful careers in special
forces of some sort, the Navy Seals, the
Army Rangers, you know, whatever, Delta
Force. And at first, post 911, they were
secunded to the CIA for, you know, quick
strike operations. And then as the years
went by, the agency decided to make many
of them official. So you put them under
global services or special activities
division or counterterrorism center and
um and they are actually CIA employees.
Others have retired from the military
and are at CIA as contractors.
So it's a much more efficient way of of
bringing them on board. But what they do
is so secret.
I mean, the the nuts and bolts of it is
so secret that they just don't talk
about that stuff. You know what they're
doing. I know what they're doing.
Everybody in the office knows what
they're doing. Nobody mentions it.
>> Can you explain like what it is that
they actually do to people?
>> Yeah. The job is to
kill or kidnap
uh and render anybody who might be a
threat to the United States, to an
American citizen or to an American
installation.
Now, at the top of the food chain, yeah,
we we want those guys to be out there
killing the Osama bin Ladens and the
Imanis of the world. We want them dead.
On the other hand,
you know, mistakes get made and you've
got people being snatched off the street
and rendered to third countries and then
tortured in those third countries only
then to have that country's intelligence
service come back to the CIA and say,
"Look, this is the wrong guy." And here
you've been torturing him mercilessly
for the last nine months, which has
happened repeatedly.
So, on the one hand, it's it's great.
Like, you know, who was it that said it
was it was Jose Rodriguez, the former
deputy director for operations, that you
need somebody who's willing to um
who's willing to take these tough
decisions, right? On the other hand,
as as American government officials,
we live by the rule of law and by the
Constitution.
And so you also have to protect the
Constitution. And just going out there
wantingly murdering people and
kidnapping people and torturing people,
that's not upholding the Constitution.
So when I when I think about ground
branch or special activities division, I
think about like you said all those
retired special operations guys, ex
Delta Force guys, ex SEAL team 6 guys
that basically go there to do the same
exact that they were doing,
>> you know, a special operations mission
set like put, like you said before, put
a charge on a door, blow it open, shoot
people in the face, and leave. But then
you hear about things like, we'll get
into the MSAD, but that you know they uh
that one it was Khaled Mashal the
attempted uh assassination in Jordan
>> where they sprayed him with poison but
like so my question is at the CIA is it
how is special activities structured? Do
they have like specialized units? There
are two different special activities
components.
one is its own division within the CIA's
director of operations called the
special activities division
before 911. That's that that were the
that was the only one, right? And they
would go do things in the cover of
darkness that nobody talked about. Then
after 9/11, the counterterrorism center
created its own special activities
group. So these were guys that were on
loan to CTC
who would go out and specifically target
terrorists, people who were planning
operations against us.
I left before they could really figure
out who was going to do what over the
long term. So I don't know how it's
structured. I do know that both
organizations still exist and a lot of
what the special activities guys do in
CTC is not assassinations, it's
kidnappings.
So,
you know, it's it's parachuting in
somewhere,
stealing a van,
and snatching somebody off the street.
and then you meet the helicopter at the
at the uh departure point and then just
fly the guy to wherever it is you're
going to fly him. It's very dangerous,
very very dangerous work cuz you're
you're not snatching people off the
street in Dubai or Abu Dhabi for
example. You're snatching them off the
street in Benghazi or Kartum or you know
Karachi or something. So, a lot of
moving parts, very, very dangerous. And
if CIA people are being killed, we
wouldn't even know it because they get
their star on the wall of honor and
there's no name attached to the star.
So, we we don't really know what's going
on with these groups.
>> So, you said what um people were on loan
to CTC from special activities?
>> No, from the military. Oh.
>> Mhm.
>> Would that be like um I forget what it
was called? The Omega program. Do Do you
Does that ring a bell?
>> I think that was uh
>> You've been after my time.
>> So that was when the CIA worked with uh
JC components. So I think it was I think
it was mainly Seal Team 6. I want to say
it wasn't uh Delta Force, but JC and
>> the CIA worked together. You know, I
will tell you in CTC at the time post
911.
Picture picture picture this. It's a big
bullpen. Got 150 people all in cubicles.
So many people I said this before that
we had to name the aisles, right? So
there's like Bin Laden Boulevard.
Seriously, Hezbollah Highway. So you
could tell people, "Oh, I I sit at the
intersection of whatever." Um, and then
around the perimeter of that big bullpen
are all the private offices. You have
the chief CTC, deputy chief for ops,
deputy chief for analysis, deputy chief
for military affairs, and then the group
chiefs, and all the big mucky mucks have
their own small private offices.
Once those guys on loan from say Seal
Team Six
came to the office, they never
interacted with any of us.
I mean, not even so much as a good
morning. And so, I mean, we we kind of
knew what these guys were there to do.
We knew who they were. They just
appeared one day, you know, in the weeks
after 9/11 and then they would vanish
for a week at a time or two weeks at a
time and then come back whispering to
each other and not interacting with you.
So, it was pretty easy to figure out who
they were and what they were up to.
I want to talk to you about CTC
specifically, but not related to CTC
necessarily. Was there a point when you
were at the agency after 9/11 where you
saw it turning into a paramilitary
organization?
>> The day after 911.
Seriously, the day after 911. Kofheer
Black.
An hour after the attacks began, Kofheer
Black stood on a chair right outside of
his office. And
it was dead silent. There were hundreds
of us, silence. And he said, "Today,
we're at war and we're all going to have
to fight. Not all of us are going to
come home.
So if you want to walk out now, walk out
and no one will think less of you.
One woman walked out and then her branch
went to went to the deputy director for
analysis and said we don't have
confidence in her leadership. And so she
was removed.
But uh I mean everybody volunteered. It
was literally within 24 hours
that we began this transition into a
paramilitary force. There was no more um
focus on recruiting spies to steal
secrets, right? It was just about
destroying al-Qaeda,
destroying it permanently.
And to tell you the truth, among core
al-Qaeda, that that core of al-Qaeda
that was based in Afghanistan, they were
destroyed by Christmas, right? The
Senate Foreign Relations Committee um
years before I joined it, of course,
came out with a with a study that
probably should have been classified and
wasn't. And they said that by the end of
2001 there were 25 active al-Qaeda
members still in Afghanistan. 25.
It had been destroyed. And everybody
else who had made their way across the
border into Pakistan we were capturing.
So it was done. Now of course there was
al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula. There
was al-Qaeda in the Islamic Levant.
There was al-Qaeda in North Africa.
They were all in al-Qaeda inspired. but
but weren't coordinating operations. And
and also, of course, we hadn't yet
killed either Bin Laden or Zawahi. But
in terms of al-Qaeda as a fighting
force, it was done by Christmas of 01.
>> Were you at the agency when they stood
up the GRS program?
>> No, I had already gone. I had already
gone, but I was dating a woman at the
time whose soontobe ex-husband was in
GRS. And she said, my husband's a GRS
officer. I said, "What's GRS?"
She looked at me kind of funny and she
told me and I said, "Oh they've
made it official."
>> So, what was it before they made it
official?
>> It was just like, "Hey, uh, you doing
anything for the next week? We're going
to need for you to do this thing. Don't
tell anybody." Yeah. Now it's an office.
>> But wasn't it wasn't it stood up to be
like security for case officers?
>> Security for leaders more than case well
no that's not true. Security for case
officers. Yes. Especially as it related
to operating in the green zone in
Baghdad. That that's where most of them
were doing their work cuz the green zone
was easily infiltrated. Yeah. Moving
from point A to point B, it took your
life into your hands every time.
those guys. I mean, you have to be a
brave son of a gun to to do a job like
that. I mean, you can say about a lot of
different agency jobs, oh, that job's
not for everybody. That job, you really
have to be fearless. You really do.
Cuz your your job is literally to throw
your body in front of the other guy so
the other guy doesn't get killed and can
complete the meeting.
Yeah, thankless.
>> What's up, guys? Thank you so much for
taking the time to watch the interview.
If you got anything out of this video at
all, please like the video, leave me a
comment, tell me what you thought of the
video, uh, tell me who you'd like to see
on the show. I really appreciate the
support. It goes a long way on these
platforms, as you guys know. Most
importantly, I have some excellent
interviews coming up in the future that
I'm really, really excited about. So,
please subscribe to the channel so you
don't miss any of them. But that's it.
Thank you for your support.